<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of closet-prayer a sermon preach'd before the Queen at White-Hall, on Sunday, Aug. 27, 1693 / by Nathanael Resbury ...</title>
            <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57058</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1128</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10183</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12827032</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12827032</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94266</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57058)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94266)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 776:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of closet-prayer a sermon preach'd before the Queen at White-Hall, on Sunday, Aug. 27, 1693 / by Nathanael Resbury ...</title>
                  <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.W. for T. Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 30.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew VI, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94266:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94266:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Of Cloſet-Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the QUEEN AT WHITE-HALL, On <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDAY, Aug.</hi> 27. 1693.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathanael Resbury,</hi> D. D. Rector of S. <hi>Paul-Shadwell,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to Their MAJESTIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Her Majeſty's Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. W.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Bennet,</hi> at the Half-Moon in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:94266:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94266:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the QUEEN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH. vi. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But thou, when thou prayeſt, enter into thy cloſet, and when thou haſt ſhut thy door, pray to thy Father which is in ſecret, and thy Father, which ſeeth thee in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, ſhall reward thee openly.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words are part of our Saviour's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes in the Mount, wherein he is cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning his Followers of thoſe uſual Schemes of Hypocriſie, by which the Phariſees had made themſelves ſo remarkable: of theſe he gives a twofold Inſtance, that of diſpoſing their Alms and Charity, which they were wont to perform, with <hi>ſound of trumpet,</hi> or open Oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the World, of what they were a doing;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94266:3"/>
               <hi>v.</hi> 2. and that of praying <hi>in the corners of the ſtreets,</hi> that they may be ſeen of Men. In oppoſition to which, he directs his Diſciples to affect (at leaſt) ſo much of Privacy in all Religious Acts, as may make it evident, their deſign is chiefly to approve themſelves before God, who ſees the heart, and values the act, from the inward intention and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign only. <hi>When thou doſt alms, let not thy left hand know, what thy right hand doth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 4. and <hi>when thou prayeſt, enter into thy cloſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a frequent Obſervation our Saviour had made elſewhere, of the horrid Hypocriſie of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and <hi>Chief</hi> among the Jews in his time; againſt which he denounces ſo many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Woes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.25, 27. and ſo on. He does it in this Chapter, both as to their Alms, and their Devotions. My Text is concern'd with their Hypocriſie, in all their Acts of pretended Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>When thou prayeſt, thou ſhalt not be as the hypocrites are: for they love to pray ſtanding in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and in the corners of the ſtreets, that they may be ſeen of men:</hi> wherein we may take notice of the poſture, and the places they choſe to pray in, in both which they might be <hi>most ſeen;</hi> their poſture, <hi>ſtanding;</hi> the place, <hi>the Synagogues and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the ſtreets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94266:3"/>
As to their poſture, of <hi>standing</hi> at their Prayers: We muſt not ſuppoſe this was unwarrantable in it ſelf, becauſe it was much in uſe, both with the Jews and Chriſtians of old. Inſomuch that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Phraſe, ſometimes, in Scripture, for praying in publick Solemnities, is, that of <hi>ſtanding before the Lord;</hi> from whence, that Jewiſh Expreſſion, <hi>Sine ſtationibus non ſubſisteret Mundus,</hi> The World could not ſubſiſt, without the <hi>ſtandings,</hi> or Prayers of the Church. And the Chriſtians, in the firſt Ages, had their certain ſeaſons, wherein they perform'd their publick Services of the Church, <hi>ſtanding;</hi> whence that term of their <hi>Stationary Days; Quum publicis ſtationibus Vota ſua perſolvit Eccleſia,</hi> When the Church perform'd her Offices of Prayer, by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Stations,</hi> or <hi>ſtanding.</hi> So that this poſture is not reflected on, as unwarrantable in it ſelf, but as choſen by the Hypocrites of that Age, that they might be the better ſeen at their Devotions.</p>
            <p>Then, for the place, they not only choſe the <hi>Synagogues,</hi> but ſtood in the <hi>chief corners of the ſtreets. In triviis</hi> (as the <hi>Latine</hi> has it). Probably, in places where three or four ſtreets met together, where Paſſengers in each of thoſe ſtreets might diſcern, and reverence their plauſible Holineſs. <hi>Verily,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>they have their reward.</hi> That is, they have what they aim'd at, and much good may it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94266:4"/>do 'em. But what good can this poor Recompence do them, when they ſhall come to be approv'd or condemn'd by him, who knows the inſides of things, and values them accordingly? <hi>But thou, when thou prayeſt, enter into thy cloſet,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That which I ſhall purſue from theſe words, ſhall be this, to lay before you the expediency and reaſonableneſs of <hi>ſecret</hi> or <hi>cloſet-Prayer.</hi> If you wou'd approve your ſelves to God indeed, you muſt be frequent in your privateſt Retirements for Prayer. The Caution in my Text directs, not only, <hi>to enter into our cloſets,</hi> but, when we are there, to <hi>ſhut</hi> our <hi>doors</hi> about us.</p>
            <p>Before I proceed to the Argument; it may not be amiſs, briefly to premiſe, that as this Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the Text, does by no means exclude the great duty incumbent upon us, both as to the Worſhip of God in publick, and alſo that in our Families: ſo, though this direction ſtrictly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that of <hi>entering into our cloſets, and ſhutting our doors, and praying to God in ſecret;</hi> it does not ſo far neceſſitate our privacy in this Action, that we are bound to take all imaginable care, that no one in the World ſhould know, or ſuſpect we do it. No, it may ſometimes be of uſe, that others ſhould underſtand our practice in this kind, that they, by our example, might learn, and be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94266:4"/>to do the ſame. How often may the Parent's, or the Maſter's <hi>known</hi> and <hi>obſerv'd</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of ſecret Prayer, inſtil a Principle into the Minds of thoſe that are under them, and that are deſirous to imitate them, that they alſo take up the ſame way; and from thence, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituate themſelves to thoſe Exerciſes of Religion, which become a future ground of their own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd Intimacies and Acquaintance with God.</p>
            <p>All the deſign of this place is, That Men ſhou'd not take up with a formal and pompous ſhew of Religion in the Acts of it: that they ſhould not court the Eye and Obſervation of the World in all they do of this kind; and make it their only deſign <hi>to be ſeen of men:</hi> but that they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light themſelves in thoſe Exerciſes of Religion, that are leſs obſerv'd by Men, wherein God and their own Conſciences are the chief Parties, and, betwixt theſe only, it appears, that we are in earneſt.</p>
            <p>In purſuing therefore this Subject, I ſhall do theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Shew upon what accounts this part of Divine Worſhip, in our moſt private and ſecret Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, becomes ſo reaſonable and neceſſary a Duty.</p>
            <p n="2">II. What ought to be our Carriage and Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour toward God, in theſe our Secrecies of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94266:5"/>Which laſt may ſerve for Application of the former.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Upon what accounts, this part of Divine Worſhip, in our moſt private and ſecret Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, becomes ſo reaſonable and neceſſary a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And this may be argued from theſe three or four Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This mainly avoids the Charge of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie in our Profeſſion, or Acts of Devotion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have, herein, the greater liberty of particularizing our Wants before God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We may, with greater collection of Mind and Thoughts, ſerve God in theſe our private Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirements.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This ſpecial Promiſe in the Text, That God that ſeeth us <hi>in ſecret,</hi> himſelf will <hi>reward us openly,</hi> will appear of great Moment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This Cuſtom of worſhipping God in ſecret, mainly avoids the Charge of Hypocriſie in our Profeſſion or Acts of Devotion. And this is that, that ſeems chiefly the occaſion of this Caution in the Text. Our Bleſſed Saviour drives plainly at it, in both the Inſtances, of Charity towards the Poor, and Devotion towards God. In the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, we are not to do as <hi>the Hypocrites do,</hi> to ſound a Trumpet before us; no, not to let our <hi>left hand know what our right hand doth.</hi> In the latter
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94266:5"/>we are not to make it our buſineſs <hi>to pray ſtanding in the ſynagogues, or in the corners of the ſtreets,</hi> but when we pray, <hi>to enter into our cloſets,</hi> &amp;c. So that to follow the reaſon of this Duty, as it is particularly grounded againſt Hypocriſie in the performance of our Worſhip toward God, it will not be amiſs to ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That Hypocriſie, where it is the only Deſign and Propoſal, in any part of Religion whatſoever, does actually deſtroy the true and juſt end of the whole undertaking.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) That we cannot ſo effectually make out our Sincerity in any Acts of Divine Worſhip, where they are only in publick, and to be <hi>ſeen of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That Hypocriſie, where it is the only Deſign, in any Act of Religion whatſoever, does actually deſtroy the true and juſt end of the whole undertaking. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Such an one does not intereſt himſelf in any one Action, or Performance of <hi>Real</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. His deſign only (as he is an Hypocrite) is to make a ſhew of doing that which he intends not. Hence he borrows his name from the Stage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>player, whoſe Employment is to perſonate Men, and Things; that is, to act <hi>their Perſons,</hi> whom they know themſelves not to <hi>be;</hi> in <hi>Things,</hi> wherein they know they are not really concern'd. Thus the Hypocrite, in all his Actions that bear a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94266:6"/>ſhow and ſemblance in Religion, his deſign only is to act a part, and not to <hi>be</hi> the Perſon, or <hi>do</hi> the Action <hi>really,</hi> which he ſeems to <hi>be</hi> or <hi>do.</hi> Thus, when ſuch an one gives Alms, he does but act the part of a <hi>truly</hi> charitable Man. He does not give in pity and commiſeration to the need of others; he does not give in conſcience toward God, or in tenderneſs for that ſtamp and Image of God, which he ſees upon his needy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or from any ſuch noble and generous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that Religion dictates: But he gives, that he may avoid the Reproach of a niggardly and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurious Man; he gives, that his Name may live after him, and may ſwell in the mouths of others, applauding him as great and generous, or devout and religious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo, while his deſign is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to perſonate the Man that is Religiouſly chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, he muſt needs, as to himſelf, deſtroy the true deſign and end of the Religious Act, becauſe he does not intereſt himſelf at all in it. So, in this Inſtance in my Text; when the Hypocrite prays, he only acts the part of the devout Man; he is not concern'd in the Realities of Devotion, becauſe he deſigns nothing, but that Men might apprehend him a zealous, holy Man; ſo that not <hi>really</hi> doing the Action he repreſents, he loſes the Privileges, or Rewards of ſuch an Action, becauſe the Action it ſelf is not <hi>really</hi> perform'd by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94266:6"/>him. Like the Actor upon the Stage, though he perſonates the Majeſty and Grandeur of a King, the wiſe Dictates and Projects of the Stateſ-man, the Valour and Conduct of the Nobleſt General; yet does not he by any means receive the <hi>real</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours due to any of theſe Characters, but, merely the Applauſe of preſent Spectators, and a little Stipend for Bread, which is all he aimed at. So our Saviour limits the Reward of this Actor to the Merits of the Performance, <hi>v.</hi> 2, 5. <hi>Verily, I ſay unto you, they have their reward.</hi> All they propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, perhaps, was the Applauſe of Men, or eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing to themſelves a preſent Intereſt, and this they may attain. But it is then only, when a Man's Sincerity in Worſhip is diſcern'd by him that ſees into the ſecrets of Hearts; it is then on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and they are ſuch only that reap the proper Fruits of Religion, becauſe he that <hi>ſeeth them in ſecret, will reward them openly.</hi> Beſides,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I may add, Hypocriſie in any Acts of Worſhip towards God, does offer ſo immediate an affront to the High and Holy One, that it muſt needs deſtroy the true ends of that Devotion, it diſſembles. For the Hypocrite, in thus doing, does either befool himſelf, and think he can mock God, as not diſcerning the inwards of his Mind, and ſo robs him of the Glories of his Omniſcience and Omnipreſence; or elſe, he has
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94266:7"/>thoſe mean thoughts of God, as eaſie enough to take up with the foppiſh ſhews and oſtentations he makes, and ſo robs him of the Honour of his infinite Holineſs and Wiſdom; or elſe, in a word, plainly defies God, that be he as holy, or wiſe, or diſcerning as he will, yet the Man will not ſet his heart aright towards him. Nor will make one ſtep further in Religion, than what mere outward Show and Oſtentation will amount to. Now there is enough, in any of theſe Inſtances of Affront done to the Divine Majeſty, that may juſtly cut the Hypocrite off from all Pretenſions to any good Reward for theſe pretended Acts of Devotion.</p>
            <p>How daring a Sinner is the Hypocrite, to think that either God does not ſee, or if he does ſee, will not concern himſelf; or if God does ſee, and will intereſt himſelf, he cares not; but, if he can attain the preſent ends of his diſſembling with the World, and God, he will run the hazard of all the reſt. No wonder that in the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures we find Hell mark'd out as the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and direct portion of the Hypocrite; that whoſoever is to be <hi>damn'd to purpoſe,</hi> has his place aſſign'd there, with the Hypocrite, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.51. <hi>The Lord of that ſervant ſhall come— and ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point him his portion with the hypocrite, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> So that, we ſee, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94266:7"/>reaſonableneſs of this Duty of keeping up the Worſhip of God in ſecret, and in our Cloſets, where God only is privy to it, that we may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by avoid the Charge of Hypocriſie in our Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when we ſee in what dangerous circumſtances the Hypocrite ſtands toward God; eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that without this cuſtom of worſhipping God in ſecret, we cannot ſo well juſtify our Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity by all other performances of publick Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which is the ſecond Particular under this Head, which I am now to make out.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) We cannot ſo effectually make out our Sincerity in any Acts of Devotion, where they are only in publick, and to be <hi>ſeen of men.</hi> For in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious uſage, chiefly, we declare, we have no Regard to any thing, but a ſenſe of our Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God, and the Zeal we have for Communion with himſelf; and that, in mere reſpect to the Obligation that lies upon us, of rendring to God his juſt Worſhip: therefore we retire from the eyes of Men, to perform it; where no other Motives ſeem'd to influence us, but the <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> or the <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of the Duty. We take no witneſs to our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions but God, and our own Conſciences: and by that, we make it evident, That, as we deſire to approve our ſelves chiefly to himſelf and our own minds; ſo, we expect no Rewards, or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage elſewhere, but from him, who <hi>ſeeth in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94266:8"/>ſecret, and will reward openly.</hi> It is true, there may be a worm of Hypocriſie at the root of our Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, even in our moſt ſecret, and unſeen dealings with God; that is, we may pleaſe and ſatisfy our minds with the thoughts that ſuch a Work, or Duty, is done, and over, urg'd to it by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcements of natural Conſcience, perſwading us of the neceſſity of ſomething of this kind. But then, as this is leſs likely, and we may generally preſume, that the conſcience of performing the Duty it ſelf, (which nothing but our regard to God, and his Commands, hath influenc'd) may alſo keep awake our care and concernment, as to the frame and diſpoſition of our minds; that we reſt not in a ſlighty performance only: ſo, it is too probable, that where any one is conſiderably frequent and diligent in attending publick Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities (in the mean time never retiring to his Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet) he is little other than an Hypocrite; at leaſt, he has not this ſatisfaction to reflect upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, nor this witneſs within of his own Truth and Sincerity, as to Religion, and the Fear of God; becauſe there are ſo many other Reaſons that might induce the Man to join with others in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Solemnities: The Cuſtoms and Faſhion of the place we live in, our natural inclination to herd and aſſociate with one another; a deſire to ſee others, and to be ſeen of them; a diverting
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94266:8"/>our ſelves for ſuch a part of time, that otherwiſe might hang upon our hands; our natural Notions of God, and neceſſity of giving him ſome kind of Worſhip: our making an intereſt with ſome good Man, that may be induc'd to value us for this appearance of Devotion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch conſiderations as theſe, may perhaps have force enough to cement us in the common bond of Worſhip toward God (and it is well that any conſiderations do ſerve to keep up the face of publick Solemnities.) But in this our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cuſtom of ſecret Prayer, there may, perhaps, appear no other motive, that we can reflect upon, as urging us to it, but the great regard we have to this indiſpenſable Command of our Bleſſed Lord, which bids us, <hi>when we pray to enter into our cloſets,</hi> and there <hi>ſhut our doors</hi> about us.</p>
            <p>So much for this <hi>firſt</hi> Head of Argument.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I may argue the Reaſonableneſs and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency of this great Duty of <hi>praying to the Father in ſecret,</hi> from this conſideration, that we have, in ſuch times, and places as theſe, the greater liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of particularizing our wants before God. There are particular concernments, wherein every pious Soul may intereſt Providence, betwixt himſelf and his gracious Father, of which publick Forms are not incluſive, at leaſt, not plainly expreſſive of them; nay, ſuch, perhaps, as may not be very
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94266:9"/>convenient to concern publick Societies withal. There may be ſome particular circumſtances of Guilt, which it is not neceſſary we ſhould lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the World, in our publick Confeſſions, which yet our gracious Father, not only allows, but encourages; nay, expects that we ſhould, in frequent Acts of Repentance, acknowledge before him, and expreſly recite them, in order to our Pardon, and Reconciliation with himſelf. There are particular wants, that preſs and urge us, which we need not trouble a multitude in knowing them; and particular ſupplies, and deliverances, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, in this or that Inſtance in Providence, which it might be impertinent, and tedious to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to rehearſe in their preſence, or return our thanks for them.</p>
            <p>But, we have one who is the Authour, and Fountain of all our Supplies and Enjoyments, and will never be wearied out, either with our freſh Supplications, or repeated Acknowledgments; with him we may have our full, and unupbraided Liberty of expoſtulating in all our fears and unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; of pouring out our Souls in all the meltings of Repentance, the paſſions of Love, Joy, Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Reſignation, with all the vigorous warmth of Converſe and Communion with God. So that, for the conveniency of declaring our wants, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging our confeſſions, repeating our thanks, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94266:9"/>our Souls in all the tranſports of Love, and Joy, and moſt free and affecting Reciprocations of his Love and Favour, <hi>when we pray, we ſhould often enter into our cloſets, and there ſhut the door, and pray to our Father which ſeeth us in ſecret.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, where Endearments are great, and the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Love more than ordinarily high, and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, there is a natural deſire of Solitude, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiredneſs, that there be no interruption, no miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, miſ-apprehended indecencies in the mutual Iſſues and Careſſes of Love. <hi>Oh my dove, that art in the clefts of the rock, and in the ſecret places of the ſtairs; let me ſee thy countenance, and let me hear thy voice; for ſweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comely</hi>—ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Cant. 2.14. How many a long night of Intercourſe and Communion with God, had <hi>David!</hi> ſometimes watering his couch with his penitential Tears; and ſometimes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the watches of it to praiſe God; that he might do both, more freely and uninterruptedly! It is not probable he could make ſuch particular confeſſions of his Murder and Adultery, ſuch fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent declarations of the weights and burdens of his Soul, in publick Solemnities, as he did in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, betwixt himſelf and God. Although after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, for the vindication both of the Juſtice and Mercy of God, and for the future Inſtruction of the Church, he had them digeſted into their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94266:10"/>Services. So that, if we conſult our own particular neceſſities, Nature it ſelf might, ſo far, direct us to purſue our own Intereſt, as to take the advantage of frequent Retirements in ſecret, to lay before God, our immediate and peculiar Concernments. And he that has been negligent, in opportunities of this nature, does thereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim himſelf one, that has as yet been poorly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken'd to any ſenſe and concernment for his own Intereſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is further highly reaſonable, That ſo we may, with greater collection of Mind and Thoughts, ſerve God in theſe our private Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The Apoſtle brings this as the Reſult of his whole Caſuiſtical Diſcourſe, about a married, and an unmarried State, <hi>viz.</hi> that all he had alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was chiefly with this deſign, <hi>That they might attend the Lord without diſtraction,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.35.</p>
            <p>And as to this Particular; there is certainly great advantage in our private retiring before God; we make our ſelves more capable of gathering up the loyns of our Minds, and recollecting our Thoughts to a greater degree of Seriouſneſs and Conſiſtency, which is the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip whatever. In publick, we may meet with many accidental Advocations, but in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, ſeldom any but thoſe of our own Minds, which are ſo much the better check'd, and kept
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94266:10"/>within bounds, as they have fewer extrinſick Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to amuze, or encumber them. So that it is not improper Advice in a modern Authour, that where any live ſo as to have the conveniencies, they would do well, to ſet apart one particular place in the Houſe, where no other concernment ſhou'd be manag'd, but their private Acts of Devotion betwixt God and their own Souls; that ſo by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom and preſcription, all their worldly or vain Thoughts might be afraid or aſham'd to enter, having been ſo long baniſh'd thence. Our Bleſſed Lord himſelf, that needed never any precautions againſt thoſe vain Avocations, which the beſt of Chriſtians are peſter'd with, yet delighted much in ſolitude for Prayer. See <hi>Mark</hi> 6.46.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The great Promiſe in the Text ought to be an abundant Argument for our fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent retiring into our Cloſets, to perform our private Supplications and Prayers there: <hi>Thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which ſeeth thee in ſecret, ſhall reward thee open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Wherein there are theſe two or three things conſiderable.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) That, be we never ſo retir'd, we have to do with one that can ſee us in the moſt ſecret receſſes, to which we can betake our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) That he himſelf that thus ſees us, has undertaken to give us our <hi>Reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Not only ſo, but, in the end, he will do it <hi>openly</hi> enough.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:94266:11"/>
(1.) Be we never ſo retir'd, we have to do with one that can ſee us in the moſt ſecret receſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to which we can betake our ſelves. This may be our abundant Comfort and Aſſurance, that we don't ſcatter our Prayers into a void and empty ſpace, or mingle our breath, only with the ſilent. Air, that makes no returns to the greateſt noiſe, but a thin and unſatisfactory <hi>Echo;</hi> but we do as eaſily with the deep and inward Groans of our Minds, without the utterance of one word, reach the ears of God, as the moſt loud and united Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations of greateſt Aſſemblies have ever done. And this, probably, is the Ground of that Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſo immediately follows my Text, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>When ye pray, uſe not vain repetitions, as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then do, for they think that they ſhall be heard for their much ſpeaking,</hi> &amp;c. In which Caution, we are not to ſuppoſe, our Saviour forbids all earneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition in Prayer, becauſe he himſelf did three times together urge the ſame thing in the ſame words, when he was in the height of his Agony, <hi>Father, if it be poſſible,</hi> &amp;c. Nor are we from hence to collect, the unneceſſary uſe of long Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, becauſe our Lord himſelf <hi>continued</hi> ſometimes <hi>all night in prayer.</hi> But, in this place, he reproaches particularly thoſe repetitions, that were us'd in the <hi>Gentile-Worſhip,</hi> with ſo much Clamour and Noiſe, as if by loud, and horrid Exclamations on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94266:11"/>their Gods were to be rouz'd and awakened to their help. Thus their Poets repreſent thoſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then-Devotions, in ſome ſuch Inſtances as theſe, when they bring in their Prieſts, for a long time together, making their noiſy and inſignificant Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther addition of any form'd Requeſt. It is ſome ſuch clamorous, and incondite Devotion as this, that <hi>Elijah</hi> derides in the Prophets of <hi>Baal;</hi> when they were crying from morning to evening, <hi>O Baal, hear us,</hi> 1 Kings 18.26, 27, 28. <hi>He mocked them, and ſaid, cry aloud: for your God is either talking, or purſuing, or in a journey, or peradventure he ſleeps, and muſt be awaked: And they cryed aloud, and cut themſelves after their manner with knives, and lancers, till the blood guſhed out</hi> — This Cuſtom of loud and weariſome repetitions, the <hi>Comoedian</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects ſharply upon; <hi>Ohe, jam deſine Deos, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor, gratulando obtundere</hi>— <q>Ceaſe, Wife, now at length, wearying the Gods with thanking them that your Daughter is found again; unleſs you meaſure them by your own Wit, and think they can underſtand nothing, but what you tell them an hundred times over.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is not Clamour, or Noiſe, that our God is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with; nor needs he it to awaken, or make him underſtand our meaning; for his Ear is in our Cloſets, and within our Hearts, to hear and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94266:12"/>obſerve the moſt ſecret and retir'd Prayer we can frame there. Poor <hi>Hamah</hi>'s Prayer, utter'd ſo much in ſecret betwixt her Soul and God, that it made <hi>Eli</hi> judge, ſhe was either drunk, or mad, yet had its effectual reward and return from God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.13, 20. And the Jews, of whom the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> conjectur'd, that they worſhipp'd nothing but the Clouds, becauſe when they brake into their Temple, and went to ſpoil the Inward San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, and the Holieſt of all, they found no Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Worſhip there; yet had the Jews, I ſay, the <hi>Shecinah,</hi> or the Divine and Glorious Preſence peculiarly reſiding in that inmoſt Receſs; where their Oracles were given, and their Sins atoned and expiated. This, therefore, in part, may be our encouragement, that he, with whom we have to do, is preſent in the moſt ſecret Retirements, and equally hears in our Cloſets, as in any other place. But further— As he ſees us, ſo,</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) He hath alſo in this Promiſe underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to <hi>reward</hi> us for thoſe Services, which no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eye is privy to. And this we find ſet in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to thoſe wretched, and trifling Rewards, which Hypocrites, by their publick Shows, and Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation of Worſhip, peculiarly deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> the Applauſe of Men and their good Opinion—<hi>Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they have their reward.</hi> They have that they look'd for. But then, as to theſe more ſecret and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94266:12"/>unſeen acts of devotion, God himſelf undertakes to give out <hi>his</hi> peculiar rewards, they having had no other regard but to him only.</p>
            <p>And what may we expect when ſo rich and bounteous a Maſter undertakes to diſpenſe it, <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> as a proper recompence! Thoſe only can beſt tell, who have met with the pleaſurable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of his Love, in their ſecrets of converſe with him. Thoſe, who in their Cloſets, have met with the joys of Pardon, after long ſtruggles of ſorrow and brokenneſs of Spirit; thoſe, who have met with great enlargements of mind, and near inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macies of Communion with God, after long dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and indiſpoſition of mind (which hath been more afflictive and diſcouraging, than all the ill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of preſent Life cou'd have been) thoſe, who have found the deſireable ſupplies of Grace, for ſubduing ſome unruly Luſts, and to help them, againſt ſome very prevalent temptations, which they have a long time conflicted with; ſuch as theſe only can tell, what it is to be <hi>at preſent</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded by God, in their privateſt retirements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
            <p>How many a pious Soul have enter'd their Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets <hi>weeping,</hi> and have <hi>born</hi> ſuch <hi>precious ſeed</hi> with them, that they have come out thence, <hi>bringing their ſheaves with them!</hi> (that I may allude to that paſſage of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſ.</hi> 126.6.) How many
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94266:13"/>have gone in with a dead and ſtreighten'd heart, that have come out again full of Heavenly and fervid Affections and Inclinations of mind to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God! And theſe are the firſt Inſtances of his rewarding them that <hi>pray</hi> to him <hi>in ſecret.</hi> And ſuch Realities are theſe, and derive ſuch ſolid and unqueſtionable Pleaſures to the mind, that all the fantaſtick Pleaſures and Rewards of this World, bear no proportion even to theſe leſs and unob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd Recompences, which ſuch do, <hi>at preſent,</hi> meet with from God. But then,</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) <hi>Laſtly,</hi> He hath further undertaken, not only to give them theſe ſecret and hidden Rewards, which good Men find in the inward Pleaſures of their own minds; but will alſo, in the great up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot of things, <hi>reward them openly.</hi> This often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times befals them in this World, in very ſignal Returns of Prayer, by many and evident Anſwers, in the preſent Diſpoſals of Divine Providence, when God has condeſcended actually to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh for ſuch, the deſires of their hearts, that they are capable of triumphing with <hi>David,</hi> and ſaying as he did, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34.6. <hi>This poor man cryed, and the Lord heard him, and delivered him out of all his troubles.</hi> This is properly an open and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick avowing the good Man's ſecret Appeals and Addreſſes to God.</p>
            <p>But then, much more <hi>openly,</hi> may they expect
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94266:13"/>to be rewarded at laſt, when, in the preſence of Angels, and the whole World of Men, that will ſtand concern'd at the Bar and Tribunal above, God himſelf will not diſdain to own and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Services, the Acts of Devotion and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that ſome have perform'd before him, in the truth and integrity of their minds, when there were no Witneſſes but his Eye only. <q>Lo this is he that made me his truſt and the ground of his dependance, and confidence, and now he finds I have not fail'd or forſaken him!</q> Thus <hi>David</hi> makes his appeals to God as the great Regiſter of his Prayers and Tears, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 56.8. <hi>Put thou my tears into thy bottle; are they not in thy book?</hi> And God himſelf by his Prophet declares how he will own ſuch at laſt, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>A Book of remembrance was written before him, for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his name, and they ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, in that day when I make up my Jewels; and I will ſpare them as a man ſpareth his own Son that ſerveth him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Happy Souls indeed! when they ſhall be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly avowed by God, and all the World ſhall come to underſtand their Wiſdom, as well as their vaſt Privileges in thoſe Secrecies of Communion and Intereſt, they once kept up betwixt themſelves and God. Which (by the way) might not a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the Imprudence and Folly of the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94266:14"/>in the management of his own great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. The main Motive, we ſee, of his Devotions, is, the Obſervation and Applauſe of Men; what an Honour would ſuch an one reckon it at laſt, to have God proclaiming his Faithfulneſs in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him, in the preſence of the whole World! but this Reward they have anticipated, in taking up with the <hi>feeble</hi> Applauſe of <hi>deluded</hi> Men in this World.</p>
            <p>And thus much may ſerve for Enquiry into the Reaſons and Grounds of Obligation, that lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us for performing this Duty of <hi>entering into our cloſets,</hi> and there praying to our <hi>Father in ſecret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Come we briefly to conſider that Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Carriage of ours, which is neceſſary, in our Secrecies of Addreſs and Communion with God. I ſhall lay it before you only in three ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Requiſites.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That when we perform theſe ſecret Acts of Worſhip, we take great care to come with all Purity of Mind.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we do it with all imaginable Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Reverence toward God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. With all Earneſtneſs and Fervour of Mind, ſuch as we may not be capable of expreſſing in our publick Solemnities, in the view of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:94266:14"/>
1. That when we perform theſe ſecret Acts of Worſhip, we take great care to come with all Purity of Mind. It is a Rule that ſhould govern all parts of Devotion; but this more eſpecially, becauſe this is a Duty wherein we pretend more intirely, againſt Hypocriſie, and more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately place our ſelves before God, becauſe no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eye ſees us.</p>
            <p>It has been the obſervation of the Heathen Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts of old, that all the Acts of Devotion, which wicked Men at any time performed, could not charm the Gods, but they proved little other than the <hi>Sacrifice of Fools.</hi> It is an excellent expreſſion of one amongſt them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. i.e. <hi>The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt abundance, and profuſeſt conſtlineſs of Oblations, bring no honour to God, except they are offered by a Divine Mind. For the Gifts and Sacrifices of Fools, or vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men, are no other than mere Food to the Fire they are thrown into.</hi> The Holy Scriptures ſpeak higher, Prov. 15.8. <hi>The ſacrifice of the wicked is an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Lord, how much more when he bringeth it with a wicked mind?</hi> Hence that blind Man, whom our Saviour had reſtored to ſight, argues with the Jews, from a common and indiſputable Principle of their own, that He muſt needs be a good Man, that had done ſo great a work. Joh. 9.31. <hi>Now
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94266:15"/>we know that God heareth not ſinners; but if a man be a worſhipper of God, and doth his will, him he hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi> Hence that Apoſtolical Injunction, 1 Tim. 2.8. <hi>I will therefore that men pray every where, lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up holy hands</hi>—It is an Obſervation that <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo Judaeus</hi> makes of the <hi>Eſſenes,</hi> whom he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as a moſt Religious Sect amongſt the Jews; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>They lift up their eyes and hands towards Heaven; <hi>eyes,</hi> that have been Religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſtrain'd from any thing unworthy that place: and <hi>hands,</hi> that have been chaſt from all the Defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Bribery and unlawful Gain; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are their Prayers of ſo great Eſteem and Value.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Agreeable to which, was that Reſolution of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> Pſ. 26.6. <hi>I will waſh mine hands in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, ſo will I compaſs thine altar, O Lord.</hi> This ought to be our eſpecial Concernment, as a moſt neceſſary Qualification in all our Dealings with God, that we lift not up filthy hands, nor breathe out our Prayers from impure and vicious Minds; becauſe we thereby deſtroy the Ground and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our Hopes and Expectations in Prayer, and expoſe our Perſons to the diſpleaſure of God, by thoſe very Acts by which we wou'd obtain his favour. <hi>If our hearts condemn us not, then have we confidence toward God. And whatſoever we ask, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of him, becauſe we keep his commandments, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94266:15"/>do thoſe things that are pleaſing in his ſight,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.21, 22.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are alſo to do it with all imaginable Humility and Reverence toward God. And, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, it is <hi>then</hi> chiefly, that we can vindicate to the <hi>Searcher of all Hearts,</hi> the truth of that Reverence and Dread we pretend toward him, when we can equally expreſs it in our <hi>cloſets,</hi> where no Eye ſees us, as in the view of a whole Aſſembly. Alas! every <hi>Hypocrite</hi> can, in the preſence of others, proſtrate himſelf; and with Eyes lift up, noiſie Groans, vehement knocking upon the Breaſt, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble geſtures of Body, and all the outward Forms and Poſtures of Reverence: He can (I ſay) dreſs and adorn his Publick Devotions, and in theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, perhaps, may have the advantage of the more devout and pious Soul. As the <hi>Ape,</hi> in its Acts of Imitation, ſometimes over-does the <hi>Man;</hi> or as the <hi>Man of Compliment,</hi> in his Courtſhips and vehement Proteſtations, will ſpeak and pretend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>Friend.</hi> But the unqueſtionable Proof of <hi>Devotion in earneſt,</hi> is, when a Man, in his priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Retirements behaves equally as humbly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently toward God, as if he knew himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the view of all the World. He then plainly ſhews he has a ſenſe of God upon his Mind in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and that he believes he is dealing with that Majeſty of Heaven and Earth, before whom the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94266:16"/>
               <hi>Angels cover their faces and their feet.</hi> It would be an ill return of the Subject upon his Lord and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, if, after his Lord ſhou'd condeſcend in ſo much Favour to him, as to retire from his Nobles and Attendants, to careſs him the freelier in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; the Subject ſhould forget the diſtance, and preſume upon all the ſacred Characters of Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, by a ſlovenly Familiarity, that would be <hi>no where</hi> allowable. How much more then ought we to judge it neceſſary, to ſhew all humble and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Demeanour toward God, though never ſo ſecretly withdrawn from the World's eye; for he does not call us into theſe Receſſes, to acquit us of our juſt Veneration, and Dread of him, but to increaſe and maintain it in more abundant Reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be haſty to utter any thing before God; for God is in heaven, and thou upon earth; therefore let thy words be few,</hi> Eccl. 5.20.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I add, <hi>laſtly,</hi> we muſt take care to do it with all earneſtneſs and fervour of Mind, which perhaps, we are not ſo capable of expreſſing, when we are in the view of others. The preſence of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers oftentimes reſtrains the inward vehemencies of Devotion, that we cannot expreſs our ſelves with that vigour and earneſtneſs of Action, which, if we were alone, we might be prompted to. The truly Religious and Devout Soul is jealous of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94266:16"/>Show and Oſtentation, and through the Modeſty of his Religion, is careful to ſuppreſs all thoſe open ways of acting it, from the obſervation of others. Like the truly affectionate <hi>Joſeph,</hi> that would rather chuſe an inner Room, to vent the Fervours of his Love and Affection, in a full flow of Tears, than in the preſence of his Brethren. But in our Cloſets, where no other eye can diſcern or follow us; we may then be as fervent and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt as we will. We may then run into the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of God, as zealouſly, and with all the warmth of Affection and Love, as ever two Friends have done, into one another's Arms, when they have no throng to interrupt or wonder at their mutual En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearments. We have then better opportunities for recollecting our wants, or our dangers; as alſo a larger ſcope of expreſſing and urging them with greater importunity. So that, as we have no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for coldneſs, or indifferency then, ſo let it be our care and endeavour, by all means, to awaken all the Powers of our Souls to the greateſt heights of Zeal and Devotion that we can arrive at, when we are alone with God.</p>
            <p>Our Lord himſelf never pray'd ſo intenſely, or wrought himſelf into ſo deep an Agony, as when he was withdrawn from his Diſciples, to pour out his Soul toward Heaven. He then pray'd, tho' in a cold Night, and in the open Air, till he ſwet drops of Blood.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94266:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Let this be our great Concernment, when we get into our Cloſets, to give all the inſtances we can, of being in earneſt then, when we need not be aſhamed of Floods of Tears, or of deepeſt Groans; but have reaſon to believe, we have to do with one that <hi>bottles</hi> up the one, and <hi>pities</hi> the other; that keeps a faithful and advantageous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter of all the Evidences of our Zeal and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where we have taken care, that no eye ſhould obſerve them but his own. Who as he <hi>ſees us in ſecret,</hi> will <hi>reward us openly.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>To God the Father, God the Son, and God the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, be all Glory and Praiſe, now and for ever.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THere is lately Printed for <hi>Tho. Bennet,</hi> Two other Sermons before the QUEEN, by Dr. <hi>Resbury.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
